A Guide to the Marcia Feuerstein Architectural Collection, 1982-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Marcia Feuerstein Architectural Collection, 1982-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Feuerstein, Marcia
Ms2007-007
3.75 Cubic Feet 3 boxes; 6 oversize folders
The collection contains information about architecture school projects and teaching information from classes led at University of Pennsylvania and Temple University. Notes, sketches, correspondence, and photographs from professional design and renovation projects as well as competition entries are included. Also included are conference and lecture materials, copies of papers and publications, and photos of artwork.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Marcia Feuerstein Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2005.
Biographical Note
Marcia Feuerstein is an associate professor at the Washington-Alexandria Architecture Center of Virginia Tech (2010). She earned her PhD. in Architecture from the University of Pennsylvania. In 1996 she joined the architecture faculty at Virginia Polytechnic Institution and State University, after teaching at the University of Pennsylvania, Temple University, and the University at Buffalo. She chaired the IAWA Board of Advisors 2001-2005, after serving as its secretary and newsletter editor. A licensed architect and member of the AIA, she has practiced in New York, Philadelphia, Buffalo, and Niagara Falls.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 3 boxes of material related to her professional career as a professor and projects as a registered architect. Included in the material are correspondences with clients, other architects, and professionals in academia. The collection contains 6 folders with her drawings and sketches, along with work as a student and a professor.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series. Series I. Personal Papers. This series is arranged into three subseries: A. Biographical Information, B. Correspondence, and C. Student work. Series II. Professional Papers. This series is arranged into five subseries: A. Writings, B. Job Search C. Presentations, D. Associations and Committees, and E. Art. Series III. Faculty Papers. This series is arranged into one subseries: A. Students' Work. Series IV. Project Records.
Adjunct Desscriptive Data
Related Materials
See also IAWA Small Collections, Ms2009-054, for photographs taken by Feuerstein.
Index Terms
Persons:
Feuerstein, Marcia
Occupations:
Architects
Subjects:
Architectural drawing -- 20th century; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings
Contents List
- Series I. Personal Papers
  - A. Biographical Information
    - Curriculum Vitae; Projects portfolio includes slides and write ups of selected projects (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B. Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Keith Walker (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C. Student Work
    - Dissertation; "The Body in Early Tewntieth Century Architecture: The Works of Oskar Schlemmer" (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II. Professional Papers
  - A. Writings
    - "Hands On," "Changing Places," "Small Town Urbanism," "Designing and Equipping Community Residences for the Developmentally Disabled" " (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Three Stas," "Fashion, the Mask, and Adolf Loos" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B. Job Search
    - Univerisity of Washington portfolio (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Texas A&M portfolio (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - UNC-Charlotte portfolio (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C. Presentations, 1986-1993
    - Environmental Design Research Association 17, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ACSA conference; Los Angeles, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Environmental Design Research Association 18; Ottawa, Canada, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ACSA conference, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Collegiate Exhibition for Excellence in Urban Design (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Society of Architectural Historians, session proposal, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - D. Associations and Committees
    - Bella Vista Neighborhood and Rite Aid (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - E. Art
    - Art photographs and photocopies (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III. Faculty Papers
  - A. Student's Work
    - Student work, syllabi (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Salem witch trial tercentary memorial design competition; correspondence, photographs, negatives, brochures, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - B. Research, Teaching Samples, and Independent Work
    - Photocopies of professional and independent work (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Past research and project proposals (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - University of Pennsylvania teaching samples (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Temple University teaching samples (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Project Records
  - BEST Milwaukee project; photographs, photocopies, montages (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - City of Buffalo teletheatre complex; conceptual photographs (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - South street community garden; sketches, correspondence (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Glen-Gery Brick Corporation project; photos, photocopies, montages (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Floating McDonald's project; photographs, photocopies, montages (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Laird residence, Folders contain correspondence, photographs, photocopies, negatives, soloman chair, children's paintings project; sketches, photocopies, floor plans, site plans, elevations, sections (Box 2, Folder 10-11, Oversize 2)
  - The PAZ building project; photographs, brochures (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - WilliWear project; photographs, photocopies, montages (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wooly Mammoth Theatre project, various project montages (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 704 Montose Street, Philadelphia project; front facade study, sketches, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Van Hook residence addition, Folders contain sketches, elevations, plans, 3-D study models, negatives, photographs, badge, panoramic photographs, sketches, plans, elevations, and inkjet prints (Box 3, Folder 1, Oversize 3)
  - Inkspot series (beginning), South Street community garden (Oversize 1)
  - Laird residence project; sketches, photocopies, floor plans, site plans, elevations, sections (Oversize 2)
  - Salem witch trials tercentary memorial design competition; pastel, sketches, diazo print, colored pencils (Oversize 4)
  - Radoccia-Feuerstein kitchen renovation; sketches, floor plans, elevations, sections (Oversize 5)
  - Posters; Design International '98, Buffalo Psychiatric Center '97, Adaptive Reuse of Historically Significant Institutional Buildings and Grounds (Oversize 6)